Finding Aid for Edgar A. Guest Papers 1898-1950
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edgar A. Guest Papers 1898-1950
Guest, Edgar A. (Edgar Albert), 1881-1959.
7 linear ft., 1 oversize volume, and two oversize folders
Special writer for the Detroit Free Press, poet, and lyricist. Scrapbooks containing copies of poetry published in newspapers, manuscripts of radio talks, fan mail, newspaper clippings of poems, greeting cards containing Guest verses, and miscellanea.
851393 Aa 2; UAs; Ac
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Edgar A. Guest (Donor no. 430 ) in 1938 and of his grandson Henry Sobel III (donor no. 9320 ) in 2003.
The collection is open for research.
Edgar A. Guest was born August 20, 1881 in Birmingham, England. He immigrated with his family to the United States in the early 1890s, settling in Detroit. In 1895 he came to work for the Detroit Free Press as an office boy. He later moved to the news department as a cub reporter. One temporary assignment had Guest clipping filler items (such as poetry) for reprinting. On his own, he began writing similar kinds of verse and offering them to the newspaper for publication. The newspaper soon gave Guest his own column which he filled with sentimental poetry and observations on daily life. His poetry appealed to Detroits's and then with republication, to the nation's common folk. Guest wrote about family, home, patriotism, and the pleasures of everyday life. Collections of his verse became enormous best selling books with titles such as A heap o' livin'; Just folks; When day is done; and Over here (written during World War I.). During the 1930s, Guest was host of two different radio programs where he read his poetry and offered his own observations on the times.
Guest was employed by the Detroit Free Press for over sixty-five years. He died August 5, 1959.
The Edgar Guest papers came to the library in two accessions. In 1938, Guest donated some galley proofs for his newspaper poetry, scripts from his radio program, sheet music containing lyrics written by Guest or based largely on his verse, and other miscellaneous publications and congratulatory correspondence. In 2003, Guest's grandson donated an extensive run of scrapbooks containing newspaper clippings of his Detroit Free Press column.
Subjects:
Authors, American--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit free press.; Guest, Edgar A. (Edgar Albert), 1881-1959.; Poets--Michigan--Detroit.; Music--Michigan--Detroit.; Poetry.
- Miscellaneous
  - Clippings about EAG, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (see also oversize folders, Ac)
  - Texts of talks given over the radio, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Congratulatory telegrams received in response to radio talk, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Book covers to EAG books (Box 1)
  - Edited galley proofs to poetry appearing in newspaper, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Greeting cards containing EAG poetry, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous printed poems (Box 1)
  - Songs and other musical compositions containing lyrics by EAG or based upon his poetry (Box 1)
  - Volume of tributary letters to be published in a Detroit newspaper at the time of the publication of his latest volume of verse, 1926 (Box 1)
  - Cartoon depicting a lost wager by the artist with EAG on a Michigan-Minnesota football game, 1925 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks
  (mainly Breakfast Table Chat newspaper column)
  - 1898-1907 (Box 2)
  - 1907-1911 (Box 3)
  - 1911-1917 (Box 4)
  - 1917-1923 (Box 5)
  - 1923-1931 (Box 6)
  - 1932-1936 (Volume 1)
  - 1937-1950 (Box 7)
  - Loose clippings (Box 7)